if we're just dealing with two
dimensions and we want to find the area
under curve we have
good tools in our toolkit all ready to
do it and i'll just remind us of our
tools so let's say that's x axis that's
the y-axis let me draw some arbitrary
function right here
that's my function f of x and let's say
we want to find the area
between x is equal to a so that's x
equal to a and x is equal to
b we saw this many many many videos ago
that the way you can think about is you
take super small widths of x or super
small changes in x we could call them
delta x's but because they're so small
we're going to call them a dx
we're going to call them a dx super
infinitesimally small changes in x and
then you multiply them times the value
of f of x at that point so you multiply
it times the height at that point which
is the value of f of x so you get f of x
times each of these infinite
infinitesimally small bases that'll give
you the area of this infinitesimally
narrow
rectangle right there and since each of
these guys are infinitely small you're
going to have an infinite number of
these rectangles in order to fill the
space you're going to have an infinite
number of these
right and so the tool we used was the
definite integral the definite integral
is a sum it's an infinite sum of these
infinitely small
areas or these infinitely small
rectangles and the notations that we use
would say we go from a
to b and we've done many videos on how
do you evaluate these things but i just
want to remind you conceptually what
this is saying this is conceptually
saying let's take a small change in x
multiply it times the height at that
point so small change in x multiply it
times the height at that point and
you're going to have an infinite number
of these because these x's are super
small they're infinitely small so you're
going to have infinite number of those
so take an infinite sum of all of those
from x is equal to a to x is equal to b
and that's just our standard definite
integral now what i want to do in this
video is extend this broaden this a
little bit to solve a
i guess maybe you could say a harder or
a broader class of problems
let's say
let's say that we are let's go to three
dimensions now and i'll just draw the x
y plane first maybe i'll keep this just
to kind of make the analogy clear
so let me draw i'm going to kind of
flatten this so we have some perspective
so let's say that this right here is the
y-axis kind of going behind the screen
as you can imagine if i just pushed on
this and knocked it down so that's the
y-axis and that is my x-axis right there
that is my x-axis and let's say i have
some path in the x-y plane
so and in order to really define a path
and the x-y plane i'll have to
parametrize or parameterize i have
trouble saying that both the x and y
variables so let's say that x
let's say that x is equal to let me
switch colors i'm using that orange too
much
let's say that x
is equal to
some function of some parameter t and
let's say y
is equal to some other function of that
same parameter t and let's say we're
going to start we're going to have t go
from
t is going to be greater than or equal
to a and then less than or equal to b
now this will define a path in the x y
plane and if you if this seems confusing
you might want to review the videos on
parametric equations but essentially you
know when t is equal to a when t is
equal to a you know you're going to have
x is equal to so at t is equal to a
you're going to have x is equal to
g of a
and you're going to have y
is equal to h of a
so you're going to have this point right
here so maybe it might be i don't know
i'll just draw an ordinary random point
here maybe that's when t is equal to a
you're going to have you're going to
plot the coordinate point g of a that's
going to be our x coordinate this is g
of a right here and then our y
coordinate is going to be h of a
right you just put t is equal to a in
each of these equations and then you get
a value for x and y so this coordinate
right here would be h of a and then you
would keep incrementing t larger and
larger until you get to b but you're
going to get a series of points that are
going to look something like
let's say it looks something like that
that right there is a curve or it's a
path in the x y plane and you know what
you're saying how does that relate to
that right now you know what are we
doing well let me just write a c here
for saying that's our curve or that's
our path
now let's say i have another function
that associates every point in the x y
plane with some value so let's say i
have some function f of x y
f of x y
what it does is it associates every
point on the x y plane with some values
so let me plot x f of x y so let me
make a vertical axis here we could do a
different color
call it the f of x y axis maybe we could
even call it the z axis if you want to
but it's some vertical axis right there
and for every point so if you give me an
x and a y and you put into my f of x y
function it's going to give you some
point so let me so i can just draw some
type of a surface that f of x y
represents and this will always become a
lot more concrete when i do some
concrete examples so say let's say that
f x y looks something like this i'm
going to try my best to draw it let's
i'll do a different color
let's say f of x y you know some surface
i'll draw a part of it
it's some surface that looks let's say
it looks something like that
that is f of x y
f of x y and remember all this is is you
give me an x and you give me a y you pop
it into f of x y it's going to give me
some third value that we're going to
plot in this vertical axis right here i
mean examples f x y
it could be i'm not saying this is a
particular case it could be x plus y
it could be f of x y these are just
examples it could be
x times y if x is 1 y is 2 f of x y will
be 1 times 2. but let's say when you
plot for every point on the on on the x
y plane when you plot f x y you get this
surface up here and we want to do
something interesting we want to figure
out not the area under this curve this
was very simple when we did it the first
time i want to find the area
the area if you imagine a curtain or a
fence that goes along this this curve
that we this pat you can imagine this
being a very straight linear path going
just along the x-axis from a to b now we
have this kind of crazy curvy path
that's going along the x-y plane and you
can imagine if you drew a wall or
curtain or a fence that went straight up
from this to
my f of x y so let me do my best effort
to draw that
so let me draw it so it's going to go up
to there and maybe this point
corresponds to there and when you draw
that curtain up it's going to intersect
it
something like that let's say it looks
something like that so this point right
here
corresponds to that point
right there so if you imagine you have a
curtain you could f x y is the roof and
this is a what i've drawn here this
curve this kind of shows you the bottom
of a of a of a wall this is some kind of
crazy wall and let me say this point it
corresponds to
well actually let me let me draw a
little bit different i want to draw
this point will correspond to some point
up here so when you when you trace where
it intersects it'll look something like
maybe like that i don't know something
like that and i'm trying my best to help
you visualize this
so this side you know maybe i'll shade
this in to make it a little solid
let's say f of x y is a little
transparent you can see but then you
have this curvy looking wall here
and the whole point of this video is how
can we figure out the area of this curvy
looking wall right this curvy looking
wall that's essentially the wall or the
fence that happens if you go from this
curve and jump up and hit the ceiling at
this f of x y so let's think a little
bit about how we can do it well if we
just use the analogy of what we did
previously we could say well look you
know
this let's call this
you know let's call let's make a little
change in distance
of our of our curve let's call that ds
ds that's a little change in distance of
my curve right there and if i multiply
that change in distance of the curve
times f of x y at that point
times f of x y that point
i'm going to get the area i am going to
get the area of that little rectangle
right there right so if i take ds my
change in my
you can imagine the arc length of this
curve at that point
so let me write you know ds is equal to
super small
super
small
change
in arc length
in arc length of of our path or of our
curve that's our ds so you can imagine
the area of that little rectangle right
there along my curvy wall is going to be
ds
d i'll make it a capital s
d s
times the height at that point well
that's f of x y
f of x y and then if i take the sum
because these are infinitely narrow
these d s's are infinitely they have
infinitely small width if i were to take
the infinite sum of all of those guys
from t is equal to a
to t is equal to b right from t is equal
to a i keep taking the sum of those
rectangles to t is equal to b right
there that will give me my area you know
i'm just using the exact same logic as i
did up there i'm not being very
mathematically rigorous but i want to
give you the intuition of what we're
doing we're really kind of just bending
the base of this thing to get a curvy
wall instead of a straight direct wall
like we had up here but you're saying
sal you know this is all abstract and
how can i even calculate something like
this this makes no sense to me i have an
s here i have an x and a y i have a t
what can i do with this and that's let's
see if we can make some headway and i
promise you when we do it with a
tangible problem the end product of this
video is going to be a little bit
hairy to look at
but when we do it with an actual problem
it'll actually i think make be very
concrete and you'll see it's not too
hard to deal with but let's see if we
can get all of this in terms of t so
first of all let's let's focus just on
this ds
so let me re-pick up the x-y-axis
so if i were to re-flip the x-y let me
switch colors it's just getting a little
monotonous
so if i were to re-flip the x-y-axis
like that i'm actually doing that same
green so you know we're dealing with the
same x y axis
so that's my y-axis
that is my x-axis and so this path right
here if i were to just draw it you know
straight up like this
it would look something like this it
would look something like this
right that's my path my my arc you know
this is when t is equal to a so this is
t is equal to a this is t is equal to b
same thing i just kind of picked it back
up so we can visualize it and we say
that we have some
change in arc length let's say this this
let me switch colors let's say that this
one right here
let's say that's some small change in
arc length and we're calling that d s
now is there some way to relate d s to
infinitely small changes in x or y
well if we think about it if we really
if we and this is all a little bit hand
wavy i'm not being mathematically
rigorous but i think it'll give you the
correct intuition
if you imagine this is you can figure
out the length of ds if you know the
lengths of the super small changes in x
and super small changes in y
so if this if this distance right here
is dx infinitesimally small change in x
this distance right here is d y
infinitesimally small change in y
right then we can figure out d s from
the pythagorean theorem you can say that
d s
d s is going to be it's the hypotenuse
of this triangle it's equal to the
square root
of
d x squared
plus
plus d y
plus d y squared so that seems to make
to make things a little bit you know we
can get rid of the ds all of a sudden so
let's rewrite this little expression
here using this sense of what ds ds is
really the square root of dx squared
plus dy squared and i'm not being very
rigorous and actually it's very hard to
be rigorous with differentials but
intuitively i think it makes a lot of
sense
so we can say that this integral the
area of this curvy curtain is going to
be the integral from t is equal to a
to t is equal to b
of
f of
x y instead of writing d s we can write
this times the square root
the square root of d x squared plus d y
squared now we at least got rid of this
big capital s but we still haven't
solved the problem of how do we solve
something you know an integral a
definite integral that looks like this
we have it in terms of t here but we
only have it in terms of x's and y's
here so we need to get everything in
terms of t
well we know x and y are both functions
of t so we can actually rewrite it like
this
we can rewrite it as
we can rewrite it as from t
is equal to a to t is equal to b
and f of x y we can write it f is a
function of x which is a function of t
and y is a func and f is also a function
of y which is also a function of t
so you give me a t i'll be able to give
you an x or a y and once you give me an
x or y i can figure out what f is so we
have that
and then we have this part right here
let's do it in orange
square root of d x squared plus d y
squared
but we still don't have things in terms
of t
we need a dt someplace here in order to
be able to evaluate this integral and
we'll see that in the next video when i
do a concrete problem but i really want
to give you a sense for the the end
product where the the formula we're
going to get this at the end product
this video where it comes from so one
thing we can do is if we if we allow
ourselves to algebraically manipulate
differentials what we could do is
let us multiply and divide by dt so one
way to think about it you could rewrite
so let me just take a do this orange
part right here let's do a little side
right here so if you take this orange
part and write it in pink and you have
dx squared
and then you have plus d y
squared and let's say we just multiply
it times dt
over dt right that's you know a small
change in t divided by a small change in
t that's one so of course you can
multiply it by that if we were to bring
this part
inside of the square root sign right so
let me let me rewrite this this is the
same thing as
1 over dt times the square root
of dx squared plus d y squared and then
times that dt
right i just wanted to write it this way
i'm just multiplying by one and here i'm
just taking this dt writing it there and
leaving this over here and now if i
wanted to bring this into the square
root sign this is the same thing this is
equal to
and i'll do it very slowly just to make
sure i'm not
allow you to believe that i'm not doing
anything shady with the algebra this is
the same thing as the square root of 1
over dt
squared let me make the radical a little
bit bigger times
dx squared
plus d y squared
and then all of that times dt
right i didn't do anything you could
just take the square root of this and
you get 1 over dt
and then if i just distribute this this
is equal to
this is equal to the square root the
square root and we have our dt out at
the end of
dx squared
or we could even write dx over dt
squared
plus
dy
over dt
squared right dx squared over dt squared
is just dx over dt squared same thing
with the y's and now all of a sudden
this starts to look pretty interesting
let's substitute this expression with
this one we said that these are
equivalent and i'll switch colors just
just for the sake of it so we have the
integral from t is equal to a let me get
our drawing back if i
from t is equal to a to t is equal to b
of f of x of t
times or f of x of t and f of or and y
of t they're both functions of t and now
instead of this expression we can write
the square root
the square root of well what's dx what's
what's the change in x with respect to
ti or whatever this parameter is what is
dx dt
dx dt is the same thing
dx dt let me write this down
dx dt
dx dt is the same thing actually i
should write it here it's the same thing
as
g prime
of t right x is a function of t the
function i wrote is g prime of t and
then this d y d t
d y d t is the same thing as h prime of
t we could say that you know this
function of t so i just want to make
that clear we know these two functions
so we can just take their derivatives
with respect to t but i'm just going to
leave it in that form so
the square root and we take
the derivative of x with respect to t
squared plus the derivative of y with
respect to t squared and then all of
that times dt and this might look like
some strange and convoluted formula but
this is actually something that we know
how to deal with we've now simplified
this strange
you know this arc length problem or this
line integral right that's essentially
what we're doing we're taking an
integral over a curve or over a line as
opposed to just an interval on the
x-axis
we've taken the strange
line integral that's in terms of the arc
length of the line and x's and y's and
we've put everything in terms of t and
i'm going to show you that in the next
video right everything is going to be
expressed in terms of t so this just
turns into a simple definite integral so
hopefully that didn't confuse you too
much i think you're going to see in the
next video that this right here is
actually a very straightforward thing to
implement and just to remind you where
it all came from i think there's i got
the parentheses right this right here
was just a change in our arc length that
whole thing right there was just a
change in arc length and this is just
the height
this is just the height
of our function at that point and we're
just summing it doing an infinite sum of
infinitely small lengths so this was the
change in our arc length times the
height this is going to have an
infinitely narrow width and you're going
to take an infinite number of these
rectangles to get the area of this and
of this entire fence or this entire
curtain and that's what this definite
integral will give us and we'll actually
apply it in the next video