so let's say you're running some kind of
company and you guys produce widgets you
produce some little trinket that people
enjoy buying and the main costs that you
have are labor
you know the the workers that you have
creating these and steal
and let's just say that your labor costs
are twenty dollars per hour
twenty dollars each hour
and then your steel costs are
uh two thousand dollars keep the numbers
kind of related to each other two
thousand dollars for every ton of steel
and then you've had your analysts work a
little bit on trying to model the
revenues you can make with your widgets
as a function of hours of labor and tons
of steel now let's say the revenue model
that they've come up with the revenue as
a function of you know hours of labor
and then s for steel let's say
is equal to about you know 100 times the
hours of labor to the power two-thirds
multiplied by the tons of steel to the
power one-third
if you put in a given amount of labor
and a given amount of steel this is
about how much money you're going to
expect to earn
and of course you want to earn as much
as you can let's say you actually have a
budget for how much you're able to spend
on all these things and your budget
the budget
is
twenty thousand dollars
you're willing to spend twenty thousand
dollars and you wanna make as much money
as you can according to this model based
on that
now this is exactly the kind of problem
that the lagrange multiplier technique
is made for we're trying to maximize
some kind of function and we have a
constraint now right now the constraint
isn't written as a formula but we can
pretty easily write it as a formula
because what makes up our budget well
it's going to be the number of hours of
labor multiplied by 20 so that's going
to be
20 dollars per hour multiplied by the
number of hours you put in
plus 2000
dollars per tons of steel
times the tons of steel that you put in
so the constraint
is basically that
you have to have these values equal
twenty thousand dollars i mean you could
say less than right you could say you're
not willing to go any more than that but
intuitively and in reality it's going to
be the case that in order to maximize
your revenues you should squeeze every
dollar that you have available and
actually hit this constraint so this
right here is the constraint of our
problem and let's go ahead and give this
guy a name the function that we're
dealing with a name
and i'm going to call it g
of
h s
which is going to be that guy
and now if you'll remember in the last
few videos the way we visualize
something like this is to think about
the set of all possible inputs so in
this case you know you might be thinking
about the hs plane
you know the number of hours of labor on
one axis the number of tons of steel on
another and this constraint well in this
case it's a it's a linear function so
this constraint is going to give us some
kind of line that tells us which pairs
of s and h are going to achieve that
constraint and then the revenue function
that we're dealing with will have
certain contours you know maybe revenues
of
ten thousand dollars have a certain
contour that looks like this and
revenues of a hundred thousand dollars
have a certain contour that looks like
this but what we want is to find which
value is barely touching the constraint
curve
just tangent to it at a given point
because that's going to be the contour
line where if you up the value by just a
little bit it would no longer intersect
with that curve there would no longer be
values of h and s that satisfy this
constraint
and the way to think about finding that
tangency is to consider the
vector perpendicular to the tangent line
to the curve at that point which
fortunately is represented by let's see
let me make some room for myself here
represented by the gradient
the gradient of our our r function the
the function whose contours this is the
revenue
and what it means for this to be tangent
to the constraint line
is that there's going to be
another vector the gradient of g of our
constraint function
that points in the same direction that's
proportional to that and typically the
way you write this is to say that the
gradient
of this function is proportional to
proportional to
the gradient of g
and this proportionality constant is
called our lagrange multiplier
it's called
the lagrange
multiplier
so let's go ahead and start working it
out let's first compute the gradient of
r
so the gradient of r
is going to be the partial derivative of
r with respect to its first variable
which is h so partial derivative with
respect to h and the second component is
its partial derivative with respect to
that second variable s
with respect to s
and in this case
that first partial derivative if we
treat h as a variable and s as a
constant then that two-thirds gets
brought down so that'll be 100
times
two-thirds times h
h to the power of well we've got to
subtract one from two-thirds when we
bring it down so that'll be negative
one-third
multiplied by s
to the one-third
and then the second component here the
partial derivative with respect to s
is going to be 100 times well now by
treating s as the variable we take down
that one-third so that's
one-third
h to the two-thirds just looks like a
constant as far as s is concerned and
then we take s to the one-third minus
one which is negative
two-thirds
negative two-thirds
great so that's the gradient of r and
now we need the gradient of g
and that one's a lot easier actually
because g is just a linear function so
when we take the gradient of g
which is its partial derivative
with respect to h partial h
and its partial derivative with respect
to s partial s
well the partial with respect to h is
just 20. the function looks like 20
times h plus something that's a constant
so that ends up being 20.
and then the partial with respect to s
likewise it's just 2 000 because it's
just some constant multiplied by s plus
a bunch of other stuff that looks like
constants
so that's great
and this means when we set the gradient
of r equal to the gradient of g the pair
of equations that we get
and let me just write it all out again
is we have this top one which i'll call
200 thirds
times and let's go ahead and do a little
simplifying while i'm rewriting things
here so h to the one third
is
really one over
h to the negative one third sorry is one
over h to the one third and that's s to
the one third so all of this that first
component is being set equal to the
first component of the gradient of g
which is 20
times lambda times this lagrange
multiplier because we're not setting the
gradients equal to each other we're just
setting them proportional to each other
so that's the first equation and then
the second one i'll go ahead and do some
simplifying while i rewrite that one
also that's going to be
thirds and then h to the two thirds so
times
h to the two thirds divided by s to the
two thirds because s to the negative two
thirds is the same as one over s to the
two-thirds
all of that
is equal to two thousand
two
thousand times lambda and the important
thing is it's that same lambda because
the entire vector has to be proportional
and i think right here is probably a
pretty good point to stop and in the
next video i'll go ahead and work
through the details and we'll land on a
solution