all of the work we've been doing so far
with line integrals has been with scalar
functions or scalar valued functions and
when i say that that just means you give
me an x and a y and you evaluate the
function at that x and y and you get
another scalar value you get it just a
number you don't get a vector so what i
want to do in this video is start to get
ourselves warmed up with regards to
vectors so that we can understand what
it means to take a line integral with
vector valued functions so let me write
down some vector valued functions
actually even a better place to start
let me
let me draw a curve or let me describe a
curve so let's put that little f of x y
to the side we can ignore it for now
let's say i have some curve c
and it's described it can be parameter
parameterized i i can't say that word as
let's say x
is equal to x of t
y
is equal to some function y of t
and let's say that this is valid for t
is between a and b so t is greater than
or equal to a
and then less than or equal to b so if i
were to just draw this
on
let me say i could draw it like this i'm
staying very abstract
right now this is not a very specific
example this is the x-axis this is the
y-axis my curve let's say this is when t
is equal to
a and then the curve might do something
might do something like this
i don't know what it does let's say it's
over there this is t is equal to
b this actual point right here will be x
of b that would be the x coordinate you
evaluate this function at b and y
of b
and this is of course when t is equal to
a the actual coordinate in r2 on this on
the cartesian coordinates will be x of a
which is this right here and then y
of a which is that right there and we've
seen that before that's just a standard
way of describing a parametric equation
or curve using two parametric equations
what i want to do now is describe this
same exact curve
using a vector valued function so if i
define a vector valued function and if
you don't remember what those are we'll
have a little bit of review here let me
say i have a vector valued function r
and i'll put a little vector
arrow on top of it in a lot of textbooks
they'll just bold it and they'll leave
scalar valued functions unbolded but
it's hard to to draw a bold so i'll put
a little vector on top
and let's say that r is a function of t
and these are going to be position
vectors
position vectors
position
position vectors and i'm specifying that
because in general when someone talks
about a vector this vector
and this vector are considered
equivalent as long as they have the same
magnitude and direction no one really
cares about what their start and end
points are as long as their direction is
the same and their length is the same
but when you talk about position vectors
you're saying no these vectors are all
going to start at
zero at the origin and when you say it's
a position vector you're implicitly
saying this is specifying a unique
position in this case it's going to be
in two-dimensional space but it could be
in three-dimensional space or really
even four-five whatever n-dimensional
space so when you say the position
vector you're literally saying okay this
vector literally specifies that point in
space
so let's let's see if we can describe
this curve
as a vector a a position vector valued
function
so we could say r of t let me switch
back to that pink color
i'll just stay in green is equal to x of
t times the unit vector in the x
direction the unit vector gets a little
carrot on top a little hat that's like
the arrow for it that just says it's a
unit vector
plus
y of t
times j if i had if i was dealing with a
curve in three dimensions i would have
plus z of t times k but we're dealing
with two dimensions right here and so
the way this works is you're just taking
your well for any t and you know and
still we're going to have t is
t is greater than or equal to a and then
less than or equal to b and this is the
exact same thing as that let me just
redraw it so let me draw our coordinates
our coordinates right here
our
axes so that's the y-axis and this is
the x-axis so when you evaluate r of a
right that's our starting point so let
me do that so r of a maybe i'll do it
right over here
our position vector valued function
evaluated at t is equal to a
is going to be equal to
x
of a
times our unit vector in the x direction
plus y of a times our unit vector in the
vertical direction or in the y direction
and what's that going to look like well
x of a
it's going x of a is this thing right
here so it's x of a times the unit
vector so it's really you know maybe the
unit vector is this long it has length 1
so now we're just going to have a length
of x of a in that direction and then
same thing in y of a it's going to be y
of a length in that direction but the
bottom line this vector right here if
you add these scaled values of these two
unit vectors you're going to get you're
going to get r of a looking something
like this
it's going to be a vector that looks
something like that
just like that it's a vector it's a
position vector that's why we're nailing
it at the origin but drawing it in
standard position and that right there
is
r
of a
now what happens if a increases a little
bit what is r of a plus a little bit and
i don't know we could call that r of a
plus delta or r of a plus h
we do a different color so let's say r
let's say we increase a a little bit r
of a
plus some small h well that's just going
to be x of
a plus h times the unit vector i
plus y times a plus h times the unit
vector j and what's that going to look
like well we're going to go a little bit
further down the curve that's like
saying the coordinate x of a plus h and
y plus a plus h which might be that
point right there so we'll go to it'll
be a new unit vector it'll be a u a new
unit vector sorry it'll be a new vector
position vector not a unit vector these
don't necessarily have length 1 that
might be right here
let me do that same color as this
so it might be just like
just like that
so that right here is r
of a plus h so you see as you keep
increasing your value of t until you get
to b these these position vectors are
going to keep specifying
we're going to keep specifying points
along this curve so the curve let me
draw the curve in a different color
the curve looks something like this it's
meant to look exactly like the curve
that i have up here and for example r of
b is going to be is going to be a vector
that looks like this it's going to be a
vector that looks like
that let me i want to draw it relatively
straight
that vector
right there
is r
r of b so hopefully you realize that
look these position vectors really are
specifying the same points on this curve
as this original i guess straight up
parametrization that we did for this
curve and i just want to do that as a
little bit of review because we're now
going to break in into the idea of
actually taking a derivative of this
vector valued function and i'll do that
in the next video