all right so today i'm going to be
talking about the lagrangian
now we've talked about lagrange
multipliers this is a highly related
concept in fact it's not really teaching
anything new this is just repackaging
stuff that we already know
so to remind you of the setup this is
going to be a constrained optimization
problem setup so we'll have some kind of
multi-variable function
f of x y and the one i have pictured
here
is
let's see it's
x squared
times e to the y
times y so what i've shown here is a
contour line for this function so that
is we say what happens if we set this
equal to some constant and we ask about
all values of x and y such that this
holds such that this function outputs
that constant and if i choose a
different constant that contour line
could look a little bit different it's
kind of nice that it has similar shapes
so that's that's the function and we're
trying to maximize it the goal is to
maximize this guy
and of course it's not just that the
reason we call it a constrained
optimization problem is because there's
some kind of constraint some kind of
other function g of x y
in this case
x squared
plus y squared
and we want to say that this has to
equal some specific amount in this case
i'm going to set it equal to 4. so we
say you can't look at any x y to
maximize this function you're limited to
the values of x and y that satisfy this
property
and i talked about this in the last
couple videos and kind of the cool thing
that we found was that
you look through the various different
contour lines of f and the maximum will
be achieved when that contour line is
just perfectly parallel to this contour
of g and you know a pretty classic
example for what you what these sorts of
things could mean or how it's used in
practice is if this was say a revenue
function for some kind of company you're
kind of modeling your revenues based on
different choices you could make running
that company and the constraint that
you'd have would be let's say a budget
so i'm just going to go ahead and write
budget or b for budget here
so you're trying to maximize revenues
and then you you have some sort of
dollar limit for what you're willing to
spend
and these of course are just kind of
made up functions you'd never have a
budget that looks like a circle and this
kind of random configuration for your
revenue but in principle you know what i
mean right
so the way that we took advantage of
this tangency property and i think this
is pretty clever let me just kind of
redraw it over here you're looking at
the point where the two functions are
just tangent to each other is that the
gradient
the gradient vector for the thing we're
maximizing which in this case is r
is going to be parallel or proportional
to the gradient vector of the constraint
which in this case is b
this can be proportional to the gradient
of the constraint
and what this means is that if we were
going to solve a set of equations what
you set up is you compute that gradient
of r and it'll involve you know two
different partial derivatives
and you set it equal not to the gradient
of b
because it's not necessarily equal to
the gradient of b
but it's proportional with some kind of
proportionality constant lambda now let
me it's kind of a squirrely lambda
lambda now that one doesn't look good
either does it
why are lambda so hard to draw all right
that looks fine so the gradient of the
revenue is proportional to the gradient
of the budget
and we did a couple examples of solving
this kind of thing this gives you two
separate equations from the two partial
derivatives and then you use this right
here this budget constraint as your
third equation
and the lagrangian the point of this
video this lagrangian function is
basically just a way to package up this
equation along with this equation into a
single entity so it's not really adding
new information and if you're solving
things by hand it doesn't really do
anything for you
but what makes it nice is that it's
something easier to hand a computer and
i'll show you what i mean so i'm going
to define the lagrangian itself which we
write with this kind of funky looking
script l
and it's a function with the same inputs
that your revenue function or the thing
that you're maximizing has along with
lambda along with that lagrange
multiplier
and the way that we define it
and i'm going to need some extra room so
i'm going to say it's equal to and kind
of define it down here the revenue
function
or whatever it is that you're maximizing
the function that you're maximizing
minus
lambda that lagrange multiplier so
that's just another input to this new
function that we're defining
multiplied by
the constraint function in this case b
evaluated at x y
minus whatever that constraint value is
in this case i put in 4 so you'd write
minus 4. if we wanted to be more general
maybe we would write
you know b for whatever your budget is
so over here you're subtracting off
little b
so this here is a new multivariable
function right it's something where you
could input x y and lambda and just kind
of plug it all in and you'd get some
kind of value and remember b in this
case is a is a constant so i'll go ahead
and write that
that
this right here is not considered a
variable this is just some constant your
variables are x y and lambda
and this would seem like a totally weird
and random thing to do if you just saw
it out of context or if it was
unmotivated but what's kind of neat and
we'll go ahead and work through this
right now
is that when you take this
is it when you take the gradient
of this function called the lagrangian
and you set it equal to zero that's
going to encapsulate all three equations
that you need
and i'll show you what i mean by that so
let's let's just remember the gradient
of l
that that's a vector
that's got three different components
since l has three different inputs
you're going to have the partial
derivative of l
with respect to x
you're going to have the partial
derivative of l
with respect to y
and then finally the partial derivative
of l
with respect to lambda our lagrange
multiplier which we're considering an
input to this function
and remember whenever we write that a
vector equals zero really we mean the
zero vector often you'll see it in bold
if it's in a textbook but what we're
really saying is we set those three
different functions the three different
partial derivatives all equal to zero
so this is just a nice like closed form
compact way of saying set all of its
partial derivatives equal to zero
and let's go ahead and think about what
those partial derivatives actually are
so this first one the partial with
respect to x
partial derivative of the lagrangian
with respect to x
it's kind of fun you know you have all
these curly symbols the curly d the
curly l it makes it look like you're
doing some truly advanced math
but really it's just kind of artificial
fanciness right
but anyway so we take the partial
derivative with respect to x and what
that equals is
well it's whatever the partial
derivative of r
with respect to x is
minus and then lambda from x's
perspective lambda just looks like a
constant
so it's going to be lambda
and then this inside the parentheses the
partial derivative of that with respect
to x
well it's going to be
whatever the partial derivative of b is
with respect to x
but subtracting off that constant that
doesn't change the derivative so this
right here is the partial derivative of
lambda with respect to x
now if you set that equal to zero and i
know i've kind of run out of room on the
right here but if you set that equal to
zero
that's the same as just saying that the
partial derivative of r with respect to
x equals lambda times the partial
derivative of b with respect to x
and if you think about what's going to
happen when you unfold this property
that the gradient of r is proportional
to the gradient of b written up here
that's just the first portion of this
right if we're setting the gradients
equal then the first component of that
is to say that the partial derivative of
r
with respect to x is equal to lambda
times the partial derivative of b with
respect to x
and then if you do this for y if we take
the partial derivative of this
lagrangian
function
with respect to y
it's very similar right it's going to be
well you just take the partial
derivative of r with respect to y in
fact it all looks just identical
whatever r is you take its partial
derivative with respect to y and then we
subtract off lambda looks like a
constant as far as y is concerned
and then that's multiplied by well
what's the partial derivative of this
this term inside the parentheses with
respect to y well it's the partial of b
with respect to y
and again again if you imagine setting
that equal to zero
that's going to be the same as setting
this partial derivative term equal to
lambda times this partial derivative
term right you kind of just bring one to
the other side
so this second component of our
lagrangian equals zero equation
is just the second function that we've
seen and a lot of these examples that
we've been doing where you set one of
the gradient vectors proportional to the
other one
and the only real difference here
from stuff that we've seen already and
even then it's not that different is
that what happens when we take the
partial derivative
of this lagrangian
with respect to lambda with respect now
i'll go ahead and give it that kind of
green lambda color here well when we
take that partial derivative if we kind
of look up at the definition of the
function
r r never has a lambda in it right it's
purely a function of x and y so that
looks just like a constant when we're
differentiating with respect to lambda
so that's just going to be zero
when we take its partial derivative
and then this next component
b of x y minus b all of that just looks
like a constant as far as lambda is
concerned right there's x's there's y
there's this constant b but none of
these things have lambdas in them so
when we take the partial derivative with
respect to lambda this just looks like
some big constant times lambda itself
so what we're going to get is i guess
we're subtracting off right up here kind
of writing a minus sign we're
subtracting off
all the stuff that was in those
parentheses b
of x y
minus
b that constant
and this whole thing if we set that
whole thing equal to zero
well that's pretty much the same as
setting b of x y minus b equal to zero
and that that's really just the same as
saying hey
we're setting b
of x y
equal to that little b right setting
this partial derivative of the
lagrangian with respect to the lagrange
multiplier equal to zero boils down to
the constraint right the third equation
that we need to solve
so in that way
setting the gradient of this lagrangian
function equal to zero is just a very
compact way of packaging three separate
equations that we need to solve the
constraint optimization problem
and i'll emphasize that in practice if
you you know if you actually see
a function for
r for the thing that you're maximizing
and a function for the budget it's much
better i think to just directly think
about these parallel gradients and kind
of solve it from there because if you
construct the lagrangian and then
compute its gradient all you're really
doing is repackaging it up only to
un-package it again
but the point of this kind of the reason
that this is a very useful construct is
that computers often have really fast
ways of solving things like this things
like the gradient of some function
equals zero
and the reason is because that's how you
solve unconstrained maximization
problems right
this is very similar to as if we just
looked at this function l out of context
and we're asked hey what is its maximum
value what are the critical points that
it has and you set its gradient equal to
zero
so kind of the whole point of this
lagrangian is that it turns our
constrained optimization problem
involving r and b and this new made-up
variable lambda into an unconstrained
optimization problem where we're just
setting the gradient of some function
equal to zero so computers can often do
that really quickly so if you just hand
the computer this function it will be
able to find you an answer whereas you
know it's harder to say hey computer i
want you to think about when the
gradients are parallel and also consider
this constraint function
it's just kind of a cleaner way to
package it all up
so with that i'll see you next video
where i'm going to talk about the
significance of this lambda term how
it's not just a ghost variable but
actually has a pretty nice
interpretation for a given constraint
problem