what i want to do in this video is to
make two parametrizations of essentially
the same curve but we're going to go
along the curve at different rates and
hopefully we'll be able to use that to
understand or get a better intuition
behind what exactly it means to take a
derivative of a position vector valued
function so let's say my first
parametrization i have x of t
is equal to t
and let's say that y of t is equal to t
squared and this is true for
t is greater than or equal to 0
and less than or equal to
2.
and if i want to write this as a
position vector valued function let me
write this x1 let me call that y1 and
let me write my position vector valued
function
i could say r1 because i'm numbering
them because i'm going to do a different
version of this exact same curve with a
slightly different parametrization so r
one of t we could say is x one of t
times i the position the unit vector i
so we'll just say t
times i
plus right this is just x of t right
here or x one of t that's the i'm
numbering them because i later have an
x2 of t
plus
t squared plus t squared times
j
and if i wanted to if i wanted to graph
this i'm going to be very careful
graphing it because i really want to
understand what the derivative means
here
so let me get my
draw
try to draw
roughly to scale
so
let's say that this is
so we get 1
two
three
four
and then let me draw my x-axis
that's good enough and my x-axis i want
it to be roughly to scale one
and two
and so at t equals zero both my x and y
coordinates are at zero or this is just
going to be the zero vector so this is
where we are at t equals zero at t
equals one this is going to be one times
i so we're going to be just like that
plus 1 times j right 1 squared is j so
we're going to be right there
and then at t is equal to 2
we're going to be at 2i so 2i you can
imagine 2 times i would be this vector
right there
right 2 times i plus 4 right 2 squared
is 4 4 times j so plus
plus this plus 4 times j right that's 4
times j if you add these two vectors
heads to tails you're going to get a
vector that goes
that endpoint is right there the vector
is going to look something like this
i don't want to
so this is what
just to make it clear what we're doing
that's r 1 of 2 right this is r 1 of 0
this is r 1 of 1. but the bottom line is
the path looks like this it's a bit it's
a parabola
so the path will look
like
that
just like that
now that's in my first parameterization
of it actually let me draw a little bit
more carefully i want to get rid of this
arrows just because i want to be a nice
clean drawing
so my it's going to be a probable well
that's that as
let me get rid of that other point too
just because it i didn't draw it exactly
where it needs to be it needs to be
right there
and my parabola or my part of my
parabola is going to look something like
that all right good enough so this is
the part the first parameterization i'm
going to do this exact same curve but
i'm going to do it slightly differently
so let's say i'll do it in different
colors
so x 2 of t let's say it equals 2t
and y
2 of t let's say it's equal to 2
t
squared or we could alternatively write
that that's the same thing as 4 t
squared just phrasing both of these guys
to the second power that's equal to 4t
squared i could write it either way and
then let's say my second
parameterization and let's say instead
of going from t equals 0 to 2 we're
going to go from t goes from 0
to
1. t goes from 0 to 1. we're going to
see it's going to we're going to cover
the exact same path
and our second
vector val or position vector valued
function
r two
of t
is going to be equal to
two t
times i
plus i could say 2t squared or 4t
squared times j and if i were to graph
this guy right here it will look like
let me draw my axes again
it's going to look the same but
it's i think useful to draw it because
i'm going to draw these the derivatives
and all of that on it later so let's see
one
two
three
four
one
two
and then let's see what happens when t
is equal to 0 when t is equal to 0
or r of 0 this all of these are going to
be 0 we just got the zero vector x and y
are both equal to 0.
when t is equal to
one half so when t is equal to one half
what are we going to get here one half
times two is one
and then we're going to get the point uh
one half squared is one fourth times 4
is 1. so when t is equal to 1 half we're
going to be at the point 1 1
and when t is equal to 1 we're going to
be the point 2
right 2
4.
so notice the curve is exactly the path
we go is exactly the same
but before we even do the derivatives
these two paths are identical i want to
think about something let's pretend that
our parameter t really is time that t is
equal to time and that tends to be the
most common that's why they call it t
it doesn't have to be time but let's say
it is time so what's happening here in
this first parametrization when we go
from zero to two seconds we cover this
path right you can imagine after one
second the dot moves here then it moves
there you can imagine a dot moving along
this curve and it takes two seconds to
do so in this situation we have a dot
moving along the same curve but it's
able to cover the same curve in only one
second and half a second it gets here it
took this guy one second to get here in
one second this guy's all the way over
here this guy takes two seconds to go
over here so in this second
parameterization even though the path is
the same the curves are the same
the dot is faster dot is
faster and i want you to keep that in
mind when we think about the derivatives
of both of these position vector valued
functions
so just remember the dot is moving
faster for every second it's getting
it's getting further along the curve
than here that's what only took them one
second now let's look at the derivatives
of both of these guys
so the derivative here so if i were to
write
r
prime
r prime r one prime of t let me do a
different color actually i already used
the orange
so let me do it
in a blue
r one
prime of t so this is the derivative now
is going to be remember it's just the
derivative of each of these times the
unit vectors so the derivative of
of t with respect to t that's just 1 so
it's 1 times i so i'll just write 1
i
plus i didn't have to write the 1 there
plus the derivative of t squared with
respect to t is 2t plus 2
t
j
and let me take the derivative over here
r
prime of t
the derivative of two t with respect to
t is two so two i
plus the derivative of four t squared is
eight t
right two times four it is
it is eight t
t
just like that
now the question is
what do their what do their respective
derivative vectors look like at
different points so let's look at i
don't know let's see let's see how fast
they're moving when time is equal to 1.
so let's take
let's take a specific point this is just
the general formula but let's take it
let's figure out what the derivative is
at a specific point so let's take r
one
when time is equal to
when time is equal to one and i wanna
take the specific point on the curve not
the specific point in time so this point
on the curve here is when time is equal
to one you could say second this point
over here which is the exact
corresponding point is when time is
equal to one half second so r one of one
is equal to and we're taking the
derivative there is equal to one i right
it's not dependent on t at all so it's 1
i
plus
2 times 1 j so plus 2
j
so at this point
the derivative of or the derivative of
our position vector function is going to
be 1i plus 2j so we can draw it like
this so if we do 1i is like this 1i
and then 2j just 2j is like that
so our derivative right there i'll do it
in the same color that i wrote it in in
this green color it's going to look like
this
it's going to look like that
and notice it looks like at least its
direction is let me do it a little bit
straighter
its direction
that's not even its direction
looks tangent to the curve it's going in
the direction that my particle is moving
remember my particle's going from here
to there so it's going in the direction
and i'm going to think about in a second
what this length of this derivative
vector is this right here just to be
clear is r one
prime it's a vector so it's the it's
it's telling us the instantaneous change
in our position vector with respect to t
or time
when time is equal to one second that's
this thing right here now let's take the
exact same position here on our curve
but that's going to occur at a different
time for this guy we already said it
only takes him
he's here at time is equal to one half
second so let's take
let's take
let me do it in i can do the same color
so here we have r2
r2 we're going to evaluate it one half
because at time is equal to one half
seconds and this is going to be equal to
2i this isn't dependent at all on time
so two
i
plus eight times the time so we're eight
time right here is one half so eight
times one half is four
so plus four
j so what does this look like
the instantaneous derivative here and
this is the derivative have to be very
clear so 2i that's let me draw some more
so 2i maybe gets us about
that far plus 4j
will get us up to right around there
plus 4j
is that vector so when you add those two
heads to tails
you get this thing
you get something that let me let me do
it like
you get something that looks like that
is something that looks like that i
didn't draw it as neatly as i would like
to but let's notice something
both of these vectors are going in the
exact same direction they're both
tangential to the path to our curve but
this vector is going is is its length
its magnitude is much larger than this
vector's magnitude and that makes sense
because i hinted at it when we first
talked about these vector valued
position functions and their derivatives
is that the length
the length
you can kind of view it as the speed the
length is equal to the speed if you
imagine time t being time and these
parametrizations are representing a dot
moving along these curves so in this
case the particle only takes a second to
go there so at this point in its path
it's moving much faster than this
particle is so if you think about it
this vector right here if you imagine
this is a position vector this is
velocity
this right here is velocity right
velocity is
a speed plus direction speed is just you
know how fast are you going velocity is
how fast you're going in what direction
i'm going this fast in and you could
calculate it using pythagorean theorem
but i just want to give you the
intuition right here i'm going that fast
in this direction here i'm going this
fast i'm going even faster that's my
magnitude but i'm still going in the
same direction so hopefully you have a
gut feeling now of what the derivative
of these position vectors really are